Poornima Ramesh

Website: https://poornimaramesh.github.io/

Email:

poornimaramesh1995@gmail.com

Data scientist with Masters in physics and PhD in machine learning, with expertise in deep learning, Bayesian statistics and statistical modelling. Currently working as senior data scientist at IDinsight, helping build solutions for governmental and non-governmental organisations to inform policy and decision making.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist IV

Mar 2023 - Current

At IDinsight, Nairobi Regional Office

- Developing and leading machine learning and data science projects
- Building machine learning and data science expertise internally
- Advocating for IDinsight's work externally, and the data science team internally

PhD Researcher in machine learning

Aug 2018 - Dec 2022

At Technical University of Munich and University of Tübingen, Germany

- Used statistical modelling, data analysis, data visualisation and numerical optimisation for improving retinal prosthetics (Sekhar et al., 2018; Corna et al., 2021)
- Employed deep learning methods from computer vision, explainable ML and statistical modelling for applications in sensory neuroscience (Ramesh et al., 2019; Ramesh et al., 2022)
- Developed Bayesian statistical inference methods using deep learning for applications in neuroscience and climate science (Ramesh et al., 2022)
- Taught masters level courses in machine learning, data science, mathematics and scientific programming
- Supervised and mentored masters and internship students in research projects
- Led collaborative research projects across different labs and team members
- Helped set up compute infrastructure for collaborative programming and reserach within the lab

Data Science Intern Aug - Oct 2021

At IDinsight, Delhi Regional Office

Using machine learning and statistical models to predict out-of-school girls from census data in rural India

- Used statistical and deep learning models including generalised linear models and random forests for predicting the number of out-of-school girls in rural India based on census data
- Learned extensive data pre-processing methods for cleaning census and survey data, as well as data visualisation and scientific writing for technical and non-technical audiences

Assistant Graduate Researcher

Aug 2013- Jun 2018

Concurrently during BS-MS studies

 Internship and masters thesis project using statistical models, data analysis, data visualisation and numerical optimisation for improving retinal prosthetics; involved collaboration with experimental neuroscience labs and retinal prosthetic manufacturers; at Forschungszentrum caesar, Germany, May 2016 - Apr 2018

- Used theoretical concepts in evolutionary dynamics, game theory, stochastic dynamics as well as probabilistic numerics, convex optimisation and numerical solvers for applications in population biology at IISER Kolkata, India, Jan - Dec 2017
- Studied and employed experimental biophysics approaches PCR amplification and confocal microscopy to explore the role of proteins associated with cell death in Alzheimer's disease, dementia, etc. at Saha Institute of Nuclear Physics, India, May 2015 - Aug 2015
- Learned and applied experimental biophysics techniques including isothermal titration calorimetry, fluorescence spectroscopy and performed data analysis to study protein denaturation in cancerous cells at Saha Institute of Nuclear Physics, India, May 2014 - Aug 2014

EDUCATION

PhD in Machine Learning
 Technical University of Munich and University of Tübingen, Germany
BS-MS Dual Degree in Physics, GPA: 9.16
 Indian Institute of Science Education and Research (IISER) Kolkata, India
Indian School Certificate, 94.40%
 Cathedral and John Connon School, Mumbai, India

SKILLS

- Programming: Python: numpy, scikit-learn, PyTorch for deep learning; MATLAB; C++; LATEX; AWS
- Languages: English, Tamil, Hindi, Bengali, German
- Mathematics: Machine learning, deep learning, statistical modelling, Bayesian statistics, signal processing, linear algebra, dynamical systems
- **Teaching:** Probabilistic machine learning, data science, linear algebra and numerical methods; supervising Masters and intern students

Professional activities